<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Meanderings</title>
    <link href="https://publii.2br02b.social/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://publii.2br02b.social" />
    <updated>2025-11-03T19:42:05-06:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Insurrectus Resistus</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://publii.2br02b.social</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Wooden Crosses</title>
        <author>
            <name>Insurrectus Resistus</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://publii.2br02b.social/wooden-crosses.html"/>
        <id>https://publii.2br02b.social/wooden-crosses.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://publii.2br02b.social/media/posts/5/1_gIbV6tBMeyHP0mJzZ_rEmA.jpg" medium="image" />

        <updated>2025-11-03T19:39:46-06:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://publii.2br02b.social/media/posts/5/1_gIbV6tBMeyHP0mJzZ_rEmA.jpg" alt="Artist: Zdzisław Beksiński" />
                    <p><a name="c1" title="c1"></a></p>
<h2>CHAPTER I</h2>
<h2>BROTHERS IN ARMS</h2>
<p> </p>
<p class="L">ALTHOUGH flowers were already scarce at this season of the year, none the less there had been found enough to bedeck all the rifles in the company, and, as rich in blossoms as a cemetery, the battalion, drums and fifes at its head, had poured helter-skelter across the town between two mute hedgerows of wide-eyed onlookers.</p>
<p>With songs and tears and laughing and drunkards' quarrellings and heart-rending good-byes they had gone on board their train. All night they had rolled along, had eaten their sardines and emptied their water-bottles by the wretched glimmer of a single candle; then, tired of their loud talk, they had gone to sleep, heaped up one against another, heads on shoulders, their legs intermingled with one another.</p>
<p>Dawn had awakened them. Hanging out their carriage doors, they scanned the villages, from which the early morning smoke was rising, for <a name="p002" title="p002"></a>traces of the recent fighting. Man hailed man from carriage to carriage.</p>
<p>"Talk about a war; not as much as a spire smashed up!"</p>
<p>Then the houses opened their eyes, the roadways came to life, and finding voice once more to shout facetious love-makings, they flung their withered flowers at the women who were on the platform at every station, waiting the unlikely return of their vanished sailormen. At every halt they eased themselves and filled the water-bottles. And at length, about ten o'clock, they detrained at Dormans, stupefied and bruised.</p>
<p>A pause of an hour for soup, and they went off by the road--no drums and fifes, no flowers, no waving handkerchiefs--and reached the village where our regiment was resting, close up behind the lines.</p>
<p>There it was just like a great fair; their weary flock was broken up into little groups--one to a company--and the quartermasters rapidly marked off for each a section or squad, which they must hunt up from farm to farm, like shelterless tramps, reading on every door the big white numbers marked in chalk.</p>
<p>Bréval, the corporal, who was coming out from the grocer's shop, found the three that were for us as they were dragging along in the street, crushed under their overladen packs, in which brand-new camp utensils shone with an insolent brilliancy.</p>
<p>"Third company, fifth squad? I'm the <a name="p003" title="p003"></a>corporal. Come on; we're billeted down at the end of the dear old town."</p>
<p>When they came into the courtyard it was Fouillard, the cook, who gave the warning.</p>
<p>"I say, lads, there's the new chums coming."</p>
<p>And flinging down in front of the blackened ashlar of his rustic fireplace the armful of paper he had just fetched up out of the cellar, he examined the new comrades.</p>
<p>"You've not let yourself be cheated," he said solemnly to Bréval. "They're as fine as new pins."</p>
<p>All of us had got up and were ringing round the three bewildered soldiers with a curious group. They stared at us and we stared at them, without a word spoken. They were arriving from behind, arriving from the towns. Yesterday they had still been walking along real streets seeing women, trains, shops; yesterday they were still living the lives of men. And we took stock of them wonderingly, enviously, as though they had been travellers disembarking from strange legendary lands.</p>
<p>"And so, you lads, they're not bothering themselves too much back there?"</p>
<p>"And dear old Panama," asked Vairon, "what are they up to there?"</p>
<p>They on their side eyed us hard, as though they had fallen among savages. Everything must have astonished them in this first meeting, our baked faces, our widely incongruous get-up; Papa Hamel's imitation otter-skin cap; the filthy, once white neckerchief Fouillard wore knotted about <a name="p004" title="p004"></a>his neck; Vairon's trousers, stiff and shining with grease; the cape Lagny wore, the liaison orderly, who had stitched an astrachan collar on to a zouave's hood; some in a "rag-picker's" round jacket, some in artillery tunics--each and everyone accoutred according to his own fashion; fat Bouffioux, who wore his identification disc in his képi, as Louis XI. wore his medals; a machine gunner with his metal shoulder-pieces and his iron gauntlet that made him look like a man-at-arms from Crécy; little Bélin with his head thrust up to the ears in an old dragoon's cap; and Broucke, "the lad from oop north," who had cut puttees for himself out of green rep curtains.</p>
<p>Sulphart alone had remained aloof out of dignity, perched upon a cask, where he was peeling potatoes with the serious, concentrated air he always assumed to go through the simplest acts of everyday existence. Scratching in his flaming bristle beard, he turned his head with a negligent air, and gazed with affected nonchalance at one of the three newcomers, a quite young fellow with a sullen look, beardless or clean-shaven--impossible to tell which--wearing a fine fancy képi and laden with a broad satchel made of moleskin.</p>
<p>"He's a real dandy lad, with his little cap like a cat's-meat dish!" scoffed Sulphart first of all half to himself.</p>
<p>Then as the other set down his kit, he discovered the satchel. Then he broke out.</p>
<p>"Hi! old boy!" he exclaimed; "did you have <a name="p005" title="p005"></a>your little game-bag made special to order for going up into the trenches? If you had a stray idea that the Boches wouldn't mark you down as much as you wanted, you might perhaps have brought along a little flag and tootled on a trumpet."</p>
<p>The new chum had straightened himself up, annoyed, with a frown making a bar across his obstinate little forehead. But all at once, put out of countenance by the jeering attitude of the old hand, he turned his head away and started to blush. The redhead was quite satisfied with his flattering success for his joke. He descended from his lofty throne, and, just to prove that he had no intention of savaging a comrade who was not responsible, he shifted his strictures higher up to the military powers whose every act and deed, according to him, were dictated by pure foolishness and a manifest desire to harass the soldier-man.</p>
<p>"I'm not saying this for you--you don't know any better yet--but those idiots that make you rub the dixies up with sabre-paste so that they may shine better. Do you fancy they don't all deserve to be shot? . . . Do they think we don't make a good enough target without that? Here, chuck us over your bag. I'll blacken it with burnt cork, and will run your bottles, your dixies, and the whole bag o' tricks through straw smoke--there's nothing better than that."</p>
<p>Lemoine, who was never more than a single pace away from Sulphart, shrugged his shoulders slowly.</p>
<p><a name="p006" title="p006"></a></p>
<p>"You're never going to drive these poor blighters daft already with your flash patter," said he reproachfully in his slow, dragging voice. "Let them alone, anyway, till they at least get well off the train."</p>
<p>The newcomer of the white satchel had taken his seat on a wheelbarrow. He seemed quite exhausted. Black runnels of sweat had traced bracketing lines from his temples to the lower part of his cheeks. He unrolled his puttees but did not venture to take off his boots--fine shooting-boots with extra wide welts.</p>
<p>"My heel is all skinned," he said to me. "My boot must be full of blood. I'm carrying such a weight."</p>
<p>Lemoine weighed his kit.</p>
<p>"That's a heavy one for sure," said he. "What on earth have you managed to bung into it? . . . Have you been putting in paving-stones?"</p>
<p>"Just what I was told to put in."</p>
<p>"It's the cartridges that weigh heavy," put in the corporal. "How many did they give you?"</p>
<p>"Two hundred and fifty. . . . but I haven't got them in my pack."</p>
<p>"Where are they, then?"</p>
<p>"In my satchel. You see, I like it better like that. Suppose we were attacked all of a sudden."</p>
<p>"Attacked?"</p>
<p>The others stared at him in amazement. Then they all started to laugh with one accord, a huge laugh that they exaggerated still further, stifling, <a name="p007" title="p007"></a>gesticulating, exchanging heavy slaps on the shoulder like caresses delivered with washerwomen's beetles.</p>
<p>"Attacked. . . . that's what he said! There's a bloke that's got them again! . . ."</p>
<p>"No, no. He's got the wind up . . ."</p>
<p>"Attacked, that's what he said. . . . He's crazy. . . . Put the dogs on him! . . ."</p>
<p>This vast candour made us laugh till we were like to choke. Papa Hamel laughed till he cried. Fouillard, for his part, was not laughing. He shrugged his shoulders, hostile all at once, already looking askance at this soldier who was much too clean and who spoke much too politely.</p>
<p>"A lad with dibs who means to come them over us," said he to Sulphart.</p>
<p>The redhead, bent only on talking more than anybody else, was considering the newcomer with compassion.</p>
<p>"But, my poor lad," said he, "you don't really suppose we are fighting that way now? That was all right for the first month. We don't fight any more now--maybe you'll never be fighting."</p>
<p>"Sure enough," said Lemoine, backing him up, "you won't fight; but you'll jabber about it all the same."</p>
<p>"You'll never fire a cartridge," prophesied Broucke, the ch'timi with the child's eyes.</p>
<p>The newcomer made no answer, doubtless thinking that the old hands were trying to pull his leg. But with his ear cocked, instead of listening to <a name="p008" title="p008"></a>Sulphart's discourse, he was hearkening to the big gun shaking the very sky with its big bellow, and he would fain have been over there already, on the far side of the blue line of hills, in the unknown plain where they were playing out the game of war with its fragrance of danger.</p>
<p class="c">. . . . .</p>
<p>The newcomer introduced himself to me. "Gilbert Demachy. . . . I was doing law. . . ."</p>
<p>And I made myself known.</p>
<p>"Jacques Larcher. I am a writer. . . ."</p>
<p>From his first appearance I knew that Gilbert would be my friend; I knew it at once from his voice, his speech, his ways. Before very long I was saying "vous" to him, and we talked of Paris. In short, I was finding someone with whom I could discourse of our books, our theatres, our cafés, of pretty girls breathing perfume. The very names I was pronouncing made me live over again for a moment all that lost happiness. I remember that Gilbert, as he sat on his barrow, had his shoeless feet on a newspaper by way of carpet. We talked on and on excitedly.</p>
<p>"You remember . . . Do you remember? . . ."</p>
<p>The boys gave the newcomers a hand in installing themselves in the stables where the squad had their sleeping-quarters, and piled their kits with ours in the manger. When they had finished, Gilbert held out two five-franc notes to stand drinks.</p>
<p><a name="p009" title="p009"></a></p>
<p>"That's that coming it over us," growled Fouillard jealous.</p>
<p>The others, full of gratitude, went back to the stable to make ready a place for the new comrade. They tossed up his straw in armfuls to freshen it, and made him a ledge round his feet. Broucke had taken respectful possession of Demachy's rubber pillow, and was amusing himself by inflating it, like a plaything, with a secret fear of wearing it out. Those who must needs change place in order to make room for the others were making the necessary move, and mutually stealing each other's straw.</p>
<p>"Here, you, big belly," said Fouillard to Bouffioux, "you're to sleep up above in the loft. Seeing that I'm sleeping just below you, take care you don't drop down on top of me in the night with your boots on my dial; I don't sleep too sound."</p>
<p>Sulphart never let go of the newcomer, bewildering him with useless advice and ridiculous tips, partly from natural good-nature, partly in return for his standing treat, but most of all to make himself important. Everybody was gay, as if they had already had their drink; Vairon in his shirt started to act the strong man in the fair, calling out his patter in a fat, common voice that had the true smack of the baffler. Ranged all about him, we took the place of the crowd. Jealous of the hit he was making, Sulphart took Lemoine by the sleeve.</p>
<p><a name="p010" title="p010"></a></p>
<p>"Come with me."</p>
<p>"Why the deuce should I go with you?" said Lemoine, always ready to oppose the redhead before falling in with him.</p>
<p>"Come along!"</p>
<p>Protesting the while, Lemoine followed him to the staircase. The notary's house, the stable of which we were humbly occupying, was a handsome rustic habitation with a high cap of slates, corbels of stucco, and a curiously painted sundial that showed noon precisely on the stroke of ten o'clock.</p>
<p>It stood to receive its guests at the top of a wide stone stair, and its newly painted shutters were of the same green as young leaves. They had remained shut since the beginning of the war. The owners had fled with the advance of the Germans, without having had time to save anything, and they had never come back. The baggage-master had at one time installed his quarters in it, but as a shell one fine morning opened a new bull's-eye window in the front, he had thought it prudent to remove himself to the other side of the district.</p>
<p>We had been definitely and specifically forbidden to set foot inside the house, every door of which was bolted and barred. Morache, the adjutant, who delighted in spoiling us with this kind of compromise, had forthwith announced that whoever transgressed the order would get a dozen bullets in his hide, without counting the <i>coup de grâce</i> to finish him. That put it in Sulphart's mind to pay a visit to the villa. Now he <a name="p011" title="p011"></a>knew it in its every nook and corner, delicately opening the doors with great kicks when an adroit leverage with a bayonet stump proved insufficient.</p>
<p>He brought Lemoine to the first floor, into a large room with light-coloured hangings.</p>
<p>"Here's what we want," said he, opening the wardrobe.</p>
<p>And flinging out linen and dresses pell-mell on to the carpeted floor, rummaging in drawers, clearing the shelves, he took his choice.</p>
<p>"I'm going to get myself up like a girl, and you'll be a man. Do you twig, donkey-face?"</p>
<p>Time to tear a few bodices in unsuccessful tryings-on, and they were able to admire themselves in the long mirror, transformed to a Shrove Tuesday bridal pair. When they made their appearance in the courtyard, arm-in-arm, there was one brief moment of stupefied wonder, and then a wild clamour greeted them.</p>
<p>"Hurrah for the wedding!" yelled Fouillard first of all.</p>
<p>The others yelled and shouted louder, and the whole squad, howling with delight, surrounded the two figures of fun. Sulphart had pulled on over his red trousers a pretty pair of lady's drawers trimmed with lace, that showed his broad crimson behind through its opening. He had donned a kind of white dressing-jacket, and on his bristling collier's head he had set a bridal wreath all awry, made of slightly yellowing orange-blossom--the wreath of the lawyer's wife, that had been reposing <a name="p012" title="p012"></a>under a glass shade. Lemoine, who was not laughing, but had rather the careworn look of a soldier on duty, had been satisfied with a Scotch kilt, a free-and-easy get-up whose regrettable lack of reticence he subdued by a frock-coat with satin lapels, and an orthodox tall hat that had been sedulously brushed the wrong way as a preliminary.</p>
<p>Little Broucke, in a state of happy amaze, was prancing behind them as if he was at a village festival.</p>
<p>"I'm off to the wedding!" he cried.</p>
<p>Singing and shouting, everybody started to dance, accompanied by Fouillard, who fancied he was providing music by banging on the black bottom of his pot with a bayonet hilt.</p>
<p>"Hurrah for the bride!" we all repeated in chorus.</p>
<p>Bréval's thin face was widened by a happy grin. All the same, he was trying to quiet us down.</p>
<p>"Not so loud! Good Lord! one of the officers will hear you."</p>
<p>Vairon had taken Sulphart round the waist, and was dancing a java with all the airs and graces of a village hop; while Lemoine, imagining himself at the local fête, was cutting pigeon's-wings and clapping his hobnailed heels together.</p>
<p>"And the feast goes on. Hurrah for the Mayor!" yelled the cook, who was vainly trying to wash his black hands by rubbing them in his perspiring forehead.</p>
<p>They were hopping one behind the other, like a <a name="p013" title="p013"></a>farandole, and laughing like urchins. The new chum followed at the tail, halting and tripping, holding on to Lagny by the hood. Sulphart, with his mouth dry as ashes, was the first to break away from the ring.</p>
<p>"Good lord, we're choking here! And that other joker who isn't coming back with the wine. So long as he doesn't let Morache grab him."</p>
<p>The thought of such a catastrophe halted the dancers.</p>
<p>"And now would be just the moment for a cherry drink," mourned Vairon.</p>
<p>"But someone else can go and buy more," said Demachy, producing two further notes. "I've laughed too much, I could do very well with a drink."</p>
<p>Respectfully or jealously, all the comrades looked on as the new chum opened his purse of fine leather, and Broucke was so overcome that he said, "Thank you," when he took the money.</p>
<p>Fouillard, who had forgotten all about his stew, had flung himself down on all fours before his blackened fire, and was puffing and blowing with might and main on the ashes, without raising a single spark out of them.</p>
<p>"Go and get some paper," he begged; "this bitch of wet wood won't catch."</p>
<p>Somebody made his way down into the cellar and brought up a pile of many-coloured papers, which he flung down near the fireplace. Stray leaves flew about, white and blue, mostly of the <a name="p014" title="p014"></a>same shape and size. They were the notary's papers. The flame as it flickered up made them flutter, and for a moment it seemed as though there could be deciphered, even in the fire itself, the fine round legal script and the insertions of peasant handwriting.</p>
<p>"I think that's a bit thick, I do," said Lemoine in his simple voice. "Those are things that should be kept. . . . Suppose somebody was burning my old folk's bits of paper for their land; I'd have him behind bars for it."</p>
<p>"Shut your jaw!" coughed Fouillard out of the smoke. "It was you yourself that wouldn't let the door be burned, and made us go and hunt for this filthy rubbish of green wood that won't catch. As if it wasn't wartime!"</p>
<p>"For sure it's wartime," said little Bélin approvingly. He had planned to make himself a waistcoat out of a frock-coat, and was very carefully cutting away the skirts.</p>
<p>"That's true, we are making war," repeated the new chum, clinking glasses with Broucke.</p>
<p>And looking at Sulphart in his drawers of fine lawn, he began to laugh.</p>
<p>"Nobody would think of it," said he. "There's lots of fun up at the front. I was certain I wouldn't be nearly as bored as in barracks."</p>
<p>Bréval, whose hollow face had resumed his two deep lines of anguish down his cheeks, looked at him and shook his head.</p>
<p>"You don't suppose that it's like this every day, <a name="p015" title="p015"></a>do you? You'd be very far out if you did, you know."</p>
<p>His nose buried in his cup, Fouillard was guffawing. Sulphart the sympathetic only shrugged his shoulders.</p>
<p>"That's not so certain," said he.</p>
<p>"If you had struck Charleroi like me," said Lagny to him, Lagny with his shrivelled old woman's face, "you wouldn't have been in such a hurry to get back to the front."</p>
<p>"And all the same you weren't in the retreat, you weren't," interrupted Vairon. "I take my oath that was no rest-camp."</p>
<p>"Aye, that was the stiffest of all, that was," agreed Lemoine.</p>
<p>"And the Marne?" asked Demachy.</p>
<p>"The Marne, that was nothing at all," said Sulphart decidedly. "It was during the retreat that we went through it most. That was where you learnt to know a man."</p>
<p>They were all the same. The retreat, that was the strategic operation they were proudest of, the one action they boasted immoderately of having shared in; it was the starting-point and foundation of all their yarns: the retreat, the terrible forced march from Charleroi to Montmirail, without halts, without food, without objective; the regiments all mixed up together, zouaves and infantry, chasseurs and engineers; wounded men, bewildered and staggering, pallid stragglers that the gendarmes bowled over; the kits and equipments <a name="p016" title="p016"></a>flung into the ditches; one-day battles, always desperate, sometimes victorious; Guise, where the German drew back; sleep deep as a stone snatched on the bank or on the road, in spite of the waggons that thundered by, crushing the sleepers' feet; grocer's shops looted, the poultry-yards they emptied, the machine gunners without mules, dragoons without horses, blacks without chiefs; the mildewed bread that men snatched from one another; the roads blocked with covered carts and bullock-waggons, with women and children all in tears; the native troops dragging goats after them, the villages shooting up in flames, the bridges that were blown up, the comrades that must needs be abandoned all bloody and foundered; and all the time, harassing the tragic column, the Boche cannon that barked without stopping. The retreat. . . . In their mouths it took on all the air and semblance of victory.</p>
<p>"I take my oath that when you read on the milestones, 'Paris, 60 kilomètres,' it gave you a funny feeling."</p>
<p>"Especially the lads of Panama," said long Vairon.</p>
<p>"And then after that," wound up Sulphart carelessly, like the commonplace epilogue of a thrilling story, "after that came the Marne."</p>
<p>"Do you remember the little melons at Tilloy? . . . Nice lot we managed to stuff in!"</p>
<p>"Aye, and the buckets of wine when we came into Gueux."</p>
<p><a name="p017" title="p017"></a></p>
<p>"I won't forget, for my part, the sausages at Montmirail. . . . You couldn't move but the big shells were on your tracks. . . . Ah! the swine!"</p>
<p>Demachy had resumed his grave look, and was eyeing these men with envy.</p>
<p>"I should have liked well to be there," said he, "to be in a victory."</p>
<p>"Sure it was a victory," conceded Sulphart, who was turning his wreath round and round in his fingers like a cap. "If you had been there you'd have been bowled over like the others, and nothing more. Ask the lads what they got at Escardes. . . . Only you people shouldn't talk without knowing. . . . All the blighters that wrote their muck about it in the papers, they'd have done better to keep their mouths shut. I was there myself--yes, and I know how it all happened. Well, we went more than fifteen days without touching our pay, from the end of August. Then after the last hot time, they paid us the lot in one go: they bunged fifteen sous at every man jack of us. That's the mere truth. And so if you see any blighters that talk to you about the Marne, you've only got to tell them one thing: that the Marne was a show that brought in fifteen sous to the lads that pulled it off. . . ."</p>
<p class="c">. . . . .</p>
<p>Night falls speedily in November. With darkness came the cold, and over there in the trenches <a name="p018" title="p018"></a>rifle-fire had waked up at the hour of the owl's awakening. We had eaten our meal in the stable, crouched and squatting on the straw, some perched up on the mangers with their legs dangling.</p>
<p>The old hands were telling complicated and brutal stories with the appropriate "and so thens" and "you remember nows," essential to the due ordering of a tale. But the newcomers, whose legs they were trying to pull, whom they meant to amaze, were no longer listening: they were half asleep, with wandering eyes and drooping chins.</p>
<p>"Time to go to bed, lads," said Bréval, unlacing his boots. "These boys have spent last night in the train."</p>
<p>Everybody went to his place with the docility of horses that knew their corner. Lemoine hesitated to trample on the fine carpet of fresh straw.</p>
<p>"That's not bad. . . . wheat that hasn't been thrashed. . . ."</p>
<p>Carefully, as he did everything, little Bélin made his bed ready. First he spread out his strip of tent canvas; then by way of a pillow, he thrust his satchel under the straw. To keep his feet warm, he slipped them into the sleeves of his vest; then he rolled himself up into his wide blanket folded in two, and very neatly, like a fisherman casting his drag-net, he threw his overcoat over his legs. By that time there was nothing to be seen but a little patch of a highly satisfied face through the opening of the knitted mountain-helmet. Bélin had retired for the night.</p>
<p><a name="p019" title="p019"></a></p>
<p>Demachy had watched every move, but not with the same admiration as I had; rather in dismay. Then he looked at the others getting ready for the night, with stupor, a kind of culminating terror. At the third who started to take off his boots, he sat upright on his little corner of straw.</p>
<p>"But you surely won't keep everything shut up here!" he exclaimed. "At least you'll be leaving the door open?"</p>
<p>The others looked at him in astonishment.</p>
<p>"No, indeed; you must be hot stuff," growled Fouillard. "The door open! Do you want us to perish of cold?"</p>
<p>The thought of sleeping there, huddled on straw with these unwashed fellows, disgusted him, terrified him. He dared not say so, but in a panic he watched his next neighbour, Fouillard, who, having methodically and slowly unrolled his muddy puttees, was pulling off his heavy boots.</p>
<p>"But it's really most unwholesome, you know," he insisted; "besides, there's this fresh straw. It ferments. . . . There have been cases of suffocation, often. . . . That's been known. . . ."</p>
<p>"Don't worry about suffocation."</p>
<p>The others were ready to sleep, lying close to keep themselves warm; Sulphart was trying to reach his boot to knock over the candle that was guttering at its last gasp. Overwhelmed, the new chum said no more. On his knees before the manger, as though he were praying to the god of cattle, he fell to hunting for a flask in his satchel.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://publii.2br02b.social/media/posts/5/1_gIbV6tBMeyHP0mJzZ_rEmA.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Artist: Zdzisław Beksiński" /></p>
                <p><a name="c1" title="c1"></a></p>
<h2>CHAPTER I</h2>
<h2>BROTHERS IN ARMS</h2>
<p> </p>
<p class="L">ALTHOUGH flowers were already scarce at this season of the year, none the less there had been found enough to bedeck all the rifles in the company, and, as rich in blossoms as a cemetery, the battalion, drums and fifes at its head, had poured helter-skelter across the town between two mute hedgerows of wide-eyed onlookers.</p>
<p>With songs and tears and laughing and drunkards' quarrellings and heart-rending good-byes they had gone on board their train. All night they had rolled along, had eaten their sardines and emptied their water-bottles by the wretched glimmer of a single candle; then, tired of their loud talk, they had gone to sleep, heaped up one against another, heads on shoulders, their legs intermingled with one another.</p>
<p>Dawn had awakened them. Hanging out their carriage doors, they scanned the villages, from which the early morning smoke was rising, for <a name="p002" title="p002"></a>traces of the recent fighting. Man hailed man from carriage to carriage.</p>
<p>"Talk about a war; not as much as a spire smashed up!"</p>
<p>Then the houses opened their eyes, the roadways came to life, and finding voice once more to shout facetious love-makings, they flung their withered flowers at the women who were on the platform at every station, waiting the unlikely return of their vanished sailormen. At every halt they eased themselves and filled the water-bottles. And at length, about ten o'clock, they detrained at Dormans, stupefied and bruised.</p>
<p>A pause of an hour for soup, and they went off by the road--no drums and fifes, no flowers, no waving handkerchiefs--and reached the village where our regiment was resting, close up behind the lines.</p>
<p>There it was just like a great fair; their weary flock was broken up into little groups--one to a company--and the quartermasters rapidly marked off for each a section or squad, which they must hunt up from farm to farm, like shelterless tramps, reading on every door the big white numbers marked in chalk.</p>
<p>Bréval, the corporal, who was coming out from the grocer's shop, found the three that were for us as they were dragging along in the street, crushed under their overladen packs, in which brand-new camp utensils shone with an insolent brilliancy.</p>
<p>"Third company, fifth squad? I'm the <a name="p003" title="p003"></a>corporal. Come on; we're billeted down at the end of the dear old town."</p>
<p>When they came into the courtyard it was Fouillard, the cook, who gave the warning.</p>
<p>"I say, lads, there's the new chums coming."</p>
<p>And flinging down in front of the blackened ashlar of his rustic fireplace the armful of paper he had just fetched up out of the cellar, he examined the new comrades.</p>
<p>"You've not let yourself be cheated," he said solemnly to Bréval. "They're as fine as new pins."</p>
<p>All of us had got up and were ringing round the three bewildered soldiers with a curious group. They stared at us and we stared at them, without a word spoken. They were arriving from behind, arriving from the towns. Yesterday they had still been walking along real streets seeing women, trains, shops; yesterday they were still living the lives of men. And we took stock of them wonderingly, enviously, as though they had been travellers disembarking from strange legendary lands.</p>
<p>"And so, you lads, they're not bothering themselves too much back there?"</p>
<p>"And dear old Panama," asked Vairon, "what are they up to there?"</p>
<p>They on their side eyed us hard, as though they had fallen among savages. Everything must have astonished them in this first meeting, our baked faces, our widely incongruous get-up; Papa Hamel's imitation otter-skin cap; the filthy, once white neckerchief Fouillard wore knotted about <a name="p004" title="p004"></a>his neck; Vairon's trousers, stiff and shining with grease; the cape Lagny wore, the liaison orderly, who had stitched an astrachan collar on to a zouave's hood; some in a "rag-picker's" round jacket, some in artillery tunics--each and everyone accoutred according to his own fashion; fat Bouffioux, who wore his identification disc in his képi, as Louis XI. wore his medals; a machine gunner with his metal shoulder-pieces and his iron gauntlet that made him look like a man-at-arms from Crécy; little Bélin with his head thrust up to the ears in an old dragoon's cap; and Broucke, "the lad from oop north," who had cut puttees for himself out of green rep curtains.</p>
<p>Sulphart alone had remained aloof out of dignity, perched upon a cask, where he was peeling potatoes with the serious, concentrated air he always assumed to go through the simplest acts of everyday existence. Scratching in his flaming bristle beard, he turned his head with a negligent air, and gazed with affected nonchalance at one of the three newcomers, a quite young fellow with a sullen look, beardless or clean-shaven--impossible to tell which--wearing a fine fancy képi and laden with a broad satchel made of moleskin.</p>
<p>"He's a real dandy lad, with his little cap like a cat's-meat dish!" scoffed Sulphart first of all half to himself.</p>
<p>Then as the other set down his kit, he discovered the satchel. Then he broke out.</p>
<p>"Hi! old boy!" he exclaimed; "did you have <a name="p005" title="p005"></a>your little game-bag made special to order for going up into the trenches? If you had a stray idea that the Boches wouldn't mark you down as much as you wanted, you might perhaps have brought along a little flag and tootled on a trumpet."</p>
<p>The new chum had straightened himself up, annoyed, with a frown making a bar across his obstinate little forehead. But all at once, put out of countenance by the jeering attitude of the old hand, he turned his head away and started to blush. The redhead was quite satisfied with his flattering success for his joke. He descended from his lofty throne, and, just to prove that he had no intention of savaging a comrade who was not responsible, he shifted his strictures higher up to the military powers whose every act and deed, according to him, were dictated by pure foolishness and a manifest desire to harass the soldier-man.</p>
<p>"I'm not saying this for you--you don't know any better yet--but those idiots that make you rub the dixies up with sabre-paste so that they may shine better. Do you fancy they don't all deserve to be shot? . . . Do they think we don't make a good enough target without that? Here, chuck us over your bag. I'll blacken it with burnt cork, and will run your bottles, your dixies, and the whole bag o' tricks through straw smoke--there's nothing better than that."</p>
<p>Lemoine, who was never more than a single pace away from Sulphart, shrugged his shoulders slowly.</p>
<p><a name="p006" title="p006"></a></p>
<p>"You're never going to drive these poor blighters daft already with your flash patter," said he reproachfully in his slow, dragging voice. "Let them alone, anyway, till they at least get well off the train."</p>
<p>The newcomer of the white satchel had taken his seat on a wheelbarrow. He seemed quite exhausted. Black runnels of sweat had traced bracketing lines from his temples to the lower part of his cheeks. He unrolled his puttees but did not venture to take off his boots--fine shooting-boots with extra wide welts.</p>
<p>"My heel is all skinned," he said to me. "My boot must be full of blood. I'm carrying such a weight."</p>
<p>Lemoine weighed his kit.</p>
<p>"That's a heavy one for sure," said he. "What on earth have you managed to bung into it? . . . Have you been putting in paving-stones?"</p>
<p>"Just what I was told to put in."</p>
<p>"It's the cartridges that weigh heavy," put in the corporal. "How many did they give you?"</p>
<p>"Two hundred and fifty. . . . but I haven't got them in my pack."</p>
<p>"Where are they, then?"</p>
<p>"In my satchel. You see, I like it better like that. Suppose we were attacked all of a sudden."</p>
<p>"Attacked?"</p>
<p>The others stared at him in amazement. Then they all started to laugh with one accord, a huge laugh that they exaggerated still further, stifling, <a name="p007" title="p007"></a>gesticulating, exchanging heavy slaps on the shoulder like caresses delivered with washerwomen's beetles.</p>
<p>"Attacked. . . . that's what he said! There's a bloke that's got them again! . . ."</p>
<p>"No, no. He's got the wind up . . ."</p>
<p>"Attacked, that's what he said. . . . He's crazy. . . . Put the dogs on him! . . ."</p>
<p>This vast candour made us laugh till we were like to choke. Papa Hamel laughed till he cried. Fouillard, for his part, was not laughing. He shrugged his shoulders, hostile all at once, already looking askance at this soldier who was much too clean and who spoke much too politely.</p>
<p>"A lad with dibs who means to come them over us," said he to Sulphart.</p>
<p>The redhead, bent only on talking more than anybody else, was considering the newcomer with compassion.</p>
<p>"But, my poor lad," said he, "you don't really suppose we are fighting that way now? That was all right for the first month. We don't fight any more now--maybe you'll never be fighting."</p>
<p>"Sure enough," said Lemoine, backing him up, "you won't fight; but you'll jabber about it all the same."</p>
<p>"You'll never fire a cartridge," prophesied Broucke, the ch'timi with the child's eyes.</p>
<p>The newcomer made no answer, doubtless thinking that the old hands were trying to pull his leg. But with his ear cocked, instead of listening to <a name="p008" title="p008"></a>Sulphart's discourse, he was hearkening to the big gun shaking the very sky with its big bellow, and he would fain have been over there already, on the far side of the blue line of hills, in the unknown plain where they were playing out the game of war with its fragrance of danger.</p>
<p class="c">. . . . .</p>
<p>The newcomer introduced himself to me. "Gilbert Demachy. . . . I was doing law. . . ."</p>
<p>And I made myself known.</p>
<p>"Jacques Larcher. I am a writer. . . ."</p>
<p>From his first appearance I knew that Gilbert would be my friend; I knew it at once from his voice, his speech, his ways. Before very long I was saying "vous" to him, and we talked of Paris. In short, I was finding someone with whom I could discourse of our books, our theatres, our cafés, of pretty girls breathing perfume. The very names I was pronouncing made me live over again for a moment all that lost happiness. I remember that Gilbert, as he sat on his barrow, had his shoeless feet on a newspaper by way of carpet. We talked on and on excitedly.</p>
<p>"You remember . . . Do you remember? . . ."</p>
<p>The boys gave the newcomers a hand in installing themselves in the stables where the squad had their sleeping-quarters, and piled their kits with ours in the manger. When they had finished, Gilbert held out two five-franc notes to stand drinks.</p>
<p><a name="p009" title="p009"></a></p>
<p>"That's that coming it over us," growled Fouillard jealous.</p>
<p>The others, full of gratitude, went back to the stable to make ready a place for the new comrade. They tossed up his straw in armfuls to freshen it, and made him a ledge round his feet. Broucke had taken respectful possession of Demachy's rubber pillow, and was amusing himself by inflating it, like a plaything, with a secret fear of wearing it out. Those who must needs change place in order to make room for the others were making the necessary move, and mutually stealing each other's straw.</p>
<p>"Here, you, big belly," said Fouillard to Bouffioux, "you're to sleep up above in the loft. Seeing that I'm sleeping just below you, take care you don't drop down on top of me in the night with your boots on my dial; I don't sleep too sound."</p>
<p>Sulphart never let go of the newcomer, bewildering him with useless advice and ridiculous tips, partly from natural good-nature, partly in return for his standing treat, but most of all to make himself important. Everybody was gay, as if they had already had their drink; Vairon in his shirt started to act the strong man in the fair, calling out his patter in a fat, common voice that had the true smack of the baffler. Ranged all about him, we took the place of the crowd. Jealous of the hit he was making, Sulphart took Lemoine by the sleeve.</p>
<p><a name="p010" title="p010"></a></p>
<p>"Come with me."</p>
<p>"Why the deuce should I go with you?" said Lemoine, always ready to oppose the redhead before falling in with him.</p>
<p>"Come along!"</p>
<p>Protesting the while, Lemoine followed him to the staircase. The notary's house, the stable of which we were humbly occupying, was a handsome rustic habitation with a high cap of slates, corbels of stucco, and a curiously painted sundial that showed noon precisely on the stroke of ten o'clock.</p>
<p>It stood to receive its guests at the top of a wide stone stair, and its newly painted shutters were of the same green as young leaves. They had remained shut since the beginning of the war. The owners had fled with the advance of the Germans, without having had time to save anything, and they had never come back. The baggage-master had at one time installed his quarters in it, but as a shell one fine morning opened a new bull's-eye window in the front, he had thought it prudent to remove himself to the other side of the district.</p>
<p>We had been definitely and specifically forbidden to set foot inside the house, every door of which was bolted and barred. Morache, the adjutant, who delighted in spoiling us with this kind of compromise, had forthwith announced that whoever transgressed the order would get a dozen bullets in his hide, without counting the <i>coup de grâce</i> to finish him. That put it in Sulphart's mind to pay a visit to the villa. Now he <a name="p011" title="p011"></a>knew it in its every nook and corner, delicately opening the doors with great kicks when an adroit leverage with a bayonet stump proved insufficient.</p>
<p>He brought Lemoine to the first floor, into a large room with light-coloured hangings.</p>
<p>"Here's what we want," said he, opening the wardrobe.</p>
<p>And flinging out linen and dresses pell-mell on to the carpeted floor, rummaging in drawers, clearing the shelves, he took his choice.</p>
<p>"I'm going to get myself up like a girl, and you'll be a man. Do you twig, donkey-face?"</p>
<p>Time to tear a few bodices in unsuccessful tryings-on, and they were able to admire themselves in the long mirror, transformed to a Shrove Tuesday bridal pair. When they made their appearance in the courtyard, arm-in-arm, there was one brief moment of stupefied wonder, and then a wild clamour greeted them.</p>
<p>"Hurrah for the wedding!" yelled Fouillard first of all.</p>
<p>The others yelled and shouted louder, and the whole squad, howling with delight, surrounded the two figures of fun. Sulphart had pulled on over his red trousers a pretty pair of lady's drawers trimmed with lace, that showed his broad crimson behind through its opening. He had donned a kind of white dressing-jacket, and on his bristling collier's head he had set a bridal wreath all awry, made of slightly yellowing orange-blossom--the wreath of the lawyer's wife, that had been reposing <a name="p012" title="p012"></a>under a glass shade. Lemoine, who was not laughing, but had rather the careworn look of a soldier on duty, had been satisfied with a Scotch kilt, a free-and-easy get-up whose regrettable lack of reticence he subdued by a frock-coat with satin lapels, and an orthodox tall hat that had been sedulously brushed the wrong way as a preliminary.</p>
<p>Little Broucke, in a state of happy amaze, was prancing behind them as if he was at a village festival.</p>
<p>"I'm off to the wedding!" he cried.</p>
<p>Singing and shouting, everybody started to dance, accompanied by Fouillard, who fancied he was providing music by banging on the black bottom of his pot with a bayonet hilt.</p>
<p>"Hurrah for the bride!" we all repeated in chorus.</p>
<p>Bréval's thin face was widened by a happy grin. All the same, he was trying to quiet us down.</p>
<p>"Not so loud! Good Lord! one of the officers will hear you."</p>
<p>Vairon had taken Sulphart round the waist, and was dancing a java with all the airs and graces of a village hop; while Lemoine, imagining himself at the local fête, was cutting pigeon's-wings and clapping his hobnailed heels together.</p>
<p>"And the feast goes on. Hurrah for the Mayor!" yelled the cook, who was vainly trying to wash his black hands by rubbing them in his perspiring forehead.</p>
<p>They were hopping one behind the other, like a <a name="p013" title="p013"></a>farandole, and laughing like urchins. The new chum followed at the tail, halting and tripping, holding on to Lagny by the hood. Sulphart, with his mouth dry as ashes, was the first to break away from the ring.</p>
<p>"Good lord, we're choking here! And that other joker who isn't coming back with the wine. So long as he doesn't let Morache grab him."</p>
<p>The thought of such a catastrophe halted the dancers.</p>
<p>"And now would be just the moment for a cherry drink," mourned Vairon.</p>
<p>"But someone else can go and buy more," said Demachy, producing two further notes. "I've laughed too much, I could do very well with a drink."</p>
<p>Respectfully or jealously, all the comrades looked on as the new chum opened his purse of fine leather, and Broucke was so overcome that he said, "Thank you," when he took the money.</p>
<p>Fouillard, who had forgotten all about his stew, had flung himself down on all fours before his blackened fire, and was puffing and blowing with might and main on the ashes, without raising a single spark out of them.</p>
<p>"Go and get some paper," he begged; "this bitch of wet wood won't catch."</p>
<p>Somebody made his way down into the cellar and brought up a pile of many-coloured papers, which he flung down near the fireplace. Stray leaves flew about, white and blue, mostly of the <a name="p014" title="p014"></a>same shape and size. They were the notary's papers. The flame as it flickered up made them flutter, and for a moment it seemed as though there could be deciphered, even in the fire itself, the fine round legal script and the insertions of peasant handwriting.</p>
<p>"I think that's a bit thick, I do," said Lemoine in his simple voice. "Those are things that should be kept. . . . Suppose somebody was burning my old folk's bits of paper for their land; I'd have him behind bars for it."</p>
<p>"Shut your jaw!" coughed Fouillard out of the smoke. "It was you yourself that wouldn't let the door be burned, and made us go and hunt for this filthy rubbish of green wood that won't catch. As if it wasn't wartime!"</p>
<p>"For sure it's wartime," said little Bélin approvingly. He had planned to make himself a waistcoat out of a frock-coat, and was very carefully cutting away the skirts.</p>
<p>"That's true, we are making war," repeated the new chum, clinking glasses with Broucke.</p>
<p>And looking at Sulphart in his drawers of fine lawn, he began to laugh.</p>
<p>"Nobody would think of it," said he. "There's lots of fun up at the front. I was certain I wouldn't be nearly as bored as in barracks."</p>
<p>Bréval, whose hollow face had resumed his two deep lines of anguish down his cheeks, looked at him and shook his head.</p>
<p>"You don't suppose that it's like this every day, <a name="p015" title="p015"></a>do you? You'd be very far out if you did, you know."</p>
<p>His nose buried in his cup, Fouillard was guffawing. Sulphart the sympathetic only shrugged his shoulders.</p>
<p>"That's not so certain," said he.</p>
<p>"If you had struck Charleroi like me," said Lagny to him, Lagny with his shrivelled old woman's face, "you wouldn't have been in such a hurry to get back to the front."</p>
<p>"And all the same you weren't in the retreat, you weren't," interrupted Vairon. "I take my oath that was no rest-camp."</p>
<p>"Aye, that was the stiffest of all, that was," agreed Lemoine.</p>
<p>"And the Marne?" asked Demachy.</p>
<p>"The Marne, that was nothing at all," said Sulphart decidedly. "It was during the retreat that we went through it most. That was where you learnt to know a man."</p>
<p>They were all the same. The retreat, that was the strategic operation they were proudest of, the one action they boasted immoderately of having shared in; it was the starting-point and foundation of all their yarns: the retreat, the terrible forced march from Charleroi to Montmirail, without halts, without food, without objective; the regiments all mixed up together, zouaves and infantry, chasseurs and engineers; wounded men, bewildered and staggering, pallid stragglers that the gendarmes bowled over; the kits and equipments <a name="p016" title="p016"></a>flung into the ditches; one-day battles, always desperate, sometimes victorious; Guise, where the German drew back; sleep deep as a stone snatched on the bank or on the road, in spite of the waggons that thundered by, crushing the sleepers' feet; grocer's shops looted, the poultry-yards they emptied, the machine gunners without mules, dragoons without horses, blacks without chiefs; the mildewed bread that men snatched from one another; the roads blocked with covered carts and bullock-waggons, with women and children all in tears; the native troops dragging goats after them, the villages shooting up in flames, the bridges that were blown up, the comrades that must needs be abandoned all bloody and foundered; and all the time, harassing the tragic column, the Boche cannon that barked without stopping. The retreat. . . . In their mouths it took on all the air and semblance of victory.</p>
<p>"I take my oath that when you read on the milestones, 'Paris, 60 kilomètres,' it gave you a funny feeling."</p>
<p>"Especially the lads of Panama," said long Vairon.</p>
<p>"And then after that," wound up Sulphart carelessly, like the commonplace epilogue of a thrilling story, "after that came the Marne."</p>
<p>"Do you remember the little melons at Tilloy? . . . Nice lot we managed to stuff in!"</p>
<p>"Aye, and the buckets of wine when we came into Gueux."</p>
<p><a name="p017" title="p017"></a></p>
<p>"I won't forget, for my part, the sausages at Montmirail. . . . You couldn't move but the big shells were on your tracks. . . . Ah! the swine!"</p>
<p>Demachy had resumed his grave look, and was eyeing these men with envy.</p>
<p>"I should have liked well to be there," said he, "to be in a victory."</p>
<p>"Sure it was a victory," conceded Sulphart, who was turning his wreath round and round in his fingers like a cap. "If you had been there you'd have been bowled over like the others, and nothing more. Ask the lads what they got at Escardes. . . . Only you people shouldn't talk without knowing. . . . All the blighters that wrote their muck about it in the papers, they'd have done better to keep their mouths shut. I was there myself--yes, and I know how it all happened. Well, we went more than fifteen days without touching our pay, from the end of August. Then after the last hot time, they paid us the lot in one go: they bunged fifteen sous at every man jack of us. That's the mere truth. And so if you see any blighters that talk to you about the Marne, you've only got to tell them one thing: that the Marne was a show that brought in fifteen sous to the lads that pulled it off. . . ."</p>
<p class="c">. . . . .</p>
<p>Night falls speedily in November. With darkness came the cold, and over there in the trenches <a name="p018" title="p018"></a>rifle-fire had waked up at the hour of the owl's awakening. We had eaten our meal in the stable, crouched and squatting on the straw, some perched up on the mangers with their legs dangling.</p>
<p>The old hands were telling complicated and brutal stories with the appropriate "and so thens" and "you remember nows," essential to the due ordering of a tale. But the newcomers, whose legs they were trying to pull, whom they meant to amaze, were no longer listening: they were half asleep, with wandering eyes and drooping chins.</p>
<p>"Time to go to bed, lads," said Bréval, unlacing his boots. "These boys have spent last night in the train."</p>
<p>Everybody went to his place with the docility of horses that knew their corner. Lemoine hesitated to trample on the fine carpet of fresh straw.</p>
<p>"That's not bad. . . . wheat that hasn't been thrashed. . . ."</p>
<p>Carefully, as he did everything, little Bélin made his bed ready. First he spread out his strip of tent canvas; then by way of a pillow, he thrust his satchel under the straw. To keep his feet warm, he slipped them into the sleeves of his vest; then he rolled himself up into his wide blanket folded in two, and very neatly, like a fisherman casting his drag-net, he threw his overcoat over his legs. By that time there was nothing to be seen but a little patch of a highly satisfied face through the opening of the knitted mountain-helmet. Bélin had retired for the night.</p>
<p><a name="p019" title="p019"></a></p>
<p>Demachy had watched every move, but not with the same admiration as I had; rather in dismay. Then he looked at the others getting ready for the night, with stupor, a kind of culminating terror. At the third who started to take off his boots, he sat upright on his little corner of straw.</p>
<p>"But you surely won't keep everything shut up here!" he exclaimed. "At least you'll be leaving the door open?"</p>
<p>The others looked at him in astonishment.</p>
<p>"No, indeed; you must be hot stuff," growled Fouillard. "The door open! Do you want us to perish of cold?"</p>
<p>The thought of sleeping there, huddled on straw with these unwashed fellows, disgusted him, terrified him. He dared not say so, but in a panic he watched his next neighbour, Fouillard, who, having methodically and slowly unrolled his muddy puttees, was pulling off his heavy boots.</p>
<p>"But it's really most unwholesome, you know," he insisted; "besides, there's this fresh straw. It ferments. . . . There have been cases of suffocation, often. . . . That's been known. . . ."</p>
<p>"Don't worry about suffocation."</p>
<p>The others were ready to sleep, lying close to keep themselves warm; Sulphart was trying to reach his boot to knock over the candle that was guttering at its last gasp. Overwhelmed, the new chum said no more. On his knees before the manger, as though he were praying to the god of cattle, he fell to hunting for a flask in his satchel.</p>

<p>"'Ware smash!" cried Sulphart, and his big shoe neatly thrown, swept the candle off to the dark.</p>
<p>"Good-night, everybody."</p>
<p>Demachy, feeling and fumbling, rolled himself up awkwardly in his blanket, and with his face entrenched in his handkerchief well sprinkled with eau-de-Cologne, he lay without moving.</p>
<p>The perfume quickly spread throughout the stable. First of all Vairon uttered his astonishment.</p>
<p>"But there's a <i>smell!</i> What on earth is it?"</p>
<p>"It stinks like a barber."</p>
<p>"That's because we're going to be suffocated," jeered Fouillard, who had tumbled to what was happening.</p>
<p>And turning over on his left side, so as not to catch the smell, he grumbled.</p>
<p>"He's got all that goes to a tart, that blighter!"</p>
<p>The new chum made no answer. The others held their tongues, wholly indifferent. Near us sleep was about to spread his brooding wings over everything. Nevertheless, in the darkness there were voices still running on.</p>
<p>"That makes fifteen days now that she hasn't written to me," confided Bréval to a pal. "She's never been so long as that before. . . . That simply torments me, you know."</p>
<p>One of the newcomers was questioning Vairon, whose rich public-house voice I recognized.</p>
<p>"When you go into rest-camp you're well received, eh?"</p>
<p><a name="p021" title="p021"></a></p>
<p>"Oo, well, they don't prod us with pitchforks, anyway; that's about all there is to it."</p>
<p>Sulphart, to send himself to sleep, was softly blackguarding Lemoine, who had promised to find some rum and had come back empty-handed.</p>
<p>"You'll show me the way to ferret out good places, you with the face fit to crush rice," he was mumbling. "Talk about an egg. . . . a billiard-ball. . . ."</p>
<p>Sleep bore them away, one after another, mingling their breathing, measured or irregular, the even respiration of a child and the outcries of troubled dreaming.</p>
<p>Outside, the night lay in wait, hearkening to the trenches. This evening they were quiet. You could hear neither the dull, all-shaking sound of the cannon, nor the dry cracking of rifle-fire. Only a machine gun was firing, round after round, without hate; you would have said a madhouse wife beating her carpet. Round about the village lay the heavy silence that broods over a freezing countryside. But suddenly, on the roadways, a deep rumbling awoke, increased, thickened, rolled towards us, and the walls began to shake. . . . The service lorries.</p>
<p>They rolled on heavily, with a jolting clamour of ironmongery. How I would have liked to go to sleep with that familiar rolling roar in my ears and in my soul! Not so long ago the motorbusses passed like that under my windows and held me awake, late, late into the night. <a name="p022" title="p022"></a>How I loathed them in those days! And now, without holding any grudge, they had nevertheless come to see me in my exile. As once upon a time, they made me start and quiver, half asleep and half awake, and I felt the walls shiver and tremble. They were coming to cradle me to sleep.</p>
<p>"It's queer, to-night there's no sound of their hard jolting on the pavement, nor rattling windows, nor belated passers-by calling them to stop. Their noise is no more than a snoring purr inside my drowsy head. They grind, they bump, they are gone. . . . Adieu, Paris!"</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>gallery test</title>
        <author>
            <name>Insurrectus Resistus</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://publii.2br02b.social/gallery-test.html"/>
        <id>https://publii.2br02b.social/gallery-test.html</id>

        <updated>2025-11-01T20:05:18-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    love these pictures and the built-in gallery works very well. don't to text
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                
  <p>
    love these pictures and the built-in gallery works very well.
  </p>

  <div  class="gallery-wrapper gallery-wrapper--wide">
    <div class="gallery" data-columns="3">
      <figure class="gallery__item">
      <a href="https://publii.2br02b.social/media/posts/1/gallery/the-lord-of-the-rings-art-by-darrell-k-sweet-1934-2011-v0-5qohc39zujzd1.webp" data-size="1080x1066">
        <img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://publii.2br02b.social/media/posts/1/gallery/the-lord-of-the-rings-art-by-darrell-k-sweet-1934-2011-v0-5qohc39zujzd1-thumbnail.webp" height="711" width="720" alt="i" >
      </a>
      <figcaption>don't</figcaption>
    </figure><figure class="gallery__item">
      <a href="https://publii.2br02b.social/media/posts/1/gallery/Gemini_Generated_Image_1ap5xx1ap5xx1ap5.png" data-size="2048x2048">
        <img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://publii.2br02b.social/media/posts/1/gallery/Gemini_Generated_Image_1ap5xx1ap5xx1ap5-thumbnail.png" height="720" width="720" alt="want" >
      </a>
      <figcaption>to</figcaption>
    </figure><figure class="gallery__item">
      <a href="https://publii.2br02b.social/media/posts/1/gallery/Gemini_Generated_Image_vfuy9pvfuy9pvfuy.png" data-size="2048x2048">
        <img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://publii.2br02b.social/media/posts/1/gallery/Gemini_Generated_Image_vfuy9pvfuy9pvfuy-thumbnail.png" height="720" width="720" alt="enter" >
      </a>
      <figcaption>text</figcaption>
    </figure><figure class="gallery__item">
      <a href="https://publii.2br02b.social/media/posts/1/gallery/Gemini_Generated_Image_esg849esg849esg8.png" data-size="1024x1024">
        <img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://publii.2br02b.social/media/posts/1/gallery/Gemini_Generated_Image_esg849esg849esg8-thumbnail.png" height="768" width="768" alt="" >
      </a>
      
    </figure><figure class="gallery__item">
      <a href="https://publii.2br02b.social/media/posts/1/gallery/Gemini_Generated_Image_imc4faimc4faimc4.png" data-size="2048x2048">
        <img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://publii.2br02b.social/media/posts/1/gallery/Gemini_Generated_Image_imc4faimc4faimc4-thumbnail.png" height="768" width="768" alt="" >
      </a>
      
    </figure><figure class="gallery__item">
      <a href="https://publii.2br02b.social/media/posts/1/gallery/Gemini_Generated_Image_lb5yhblb5yhblb5y.png" data-size="2048x2048">
        <img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://publii.2br02b.social/media/posts/1/gallery/Gemini_Generated_Image_lb5yhblb5yhblb5y-thumbnail.png" height="768" width="768" alt="" >
      </a>
      
    </figure><figure class="gallery__item">
      <a href="https://publii.2br02b.social/media/posts/1/gallery/Gemini_Generated_Image_sjashbsjashbsjas.png" data-size="2048x2048">
        <img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://publii.2br02b.social/media/posts/1/gallery/Gemini_Generated_Image_sjashbsjashbsjas-thumbnail.png" height="768" width="768" alt="" >
      </a>
      
    </figure><figure class="gallery__item">
      <a href="https://publii.2br02b.social/media/posts/1/gallery/Gemini_Generated_Image_tqk02ktqk02ktqk0.png" data-size="2048x2048">
        <img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://publii.2br02b.social/media/posts/1/gallery/Gemini_Generated_Image_tqk02ktqk02ktqk0-thumbnail.png" height="768" width="768" alt="" >
      </a>
      
    </figure>
    </div>
  </div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
